There are those who absolutely refused
to stop pushing forward.
決して立ち止まらなかった者たちがいる
On occasion, they become one with their
personal convictions, transforming into karma itself.
彼らは時として　自らの信念と同化し
業そのものに変わってしまう
These beings, who while human,
have also transcended humanity,
人でありつつ　人を越えてしまった者たちは
and continue to watch over everything
with the gaze of inhuman eyes.
人の目ならざる眼差しで　すべてを見つめ続ける
Everyone, unable to resist, goes down in
誰もが逆らえずに潜っていく
Make those eyes shine brighter than a torch
その目を灯火より輝かせて
The destination we are aiming for is deep
目指す先は深く まっすぐに迷い込む
We squarely lose our way
The trap of the open-mouthed netherworld
口開けた奈落の罠 真実の跡を追いかけよう
Let's chase the traces of truth
If an answer can be found now, we don't mind losing it all
今答えが　見つかるなら　全部失くしてもいい
The echo is still reverberating
その声を　離さないように　木霊がまだ響いてる
So that we do not part with that voice
The compass is always
羅針盤はずっと 闇を指したまま逃げ場のない 方へ
Pointed to the darkness
Where there is no escape
In that direction
Even if that is a curse
それが呪いでも　鼓動は本物
The pulse is the real thing
Never again will the yearning stop
二度と憧れは　止まらない
The Unmovable Sovereign
The very best of the cave raiders: the White Whistles.
探窟家の最高峰　白笛
Armed with Relics of the netherworld
they've personally excavated,
彼らは自らが発掘した奈落の遺物で武装し
they are each known by titles
that uniquely personify them.
それぞれを体現した異名で呼ばれている
Even among them, one stands unrivaled
in terms of physical strength:
その中でも無双の怪力を持つのが
the Unmovable Sovereign, Ozen the Immovable.
「不動卿」動かざるオーゼンだ
So then, are the stories about how she pulled up
a gondola with 30 people inside,
じゃあ　30人乗ったゴンドラを引き上げたとか
or how she supported a boulder
that was 10 meters across, all really true?
10メートルもある岩を支えたってのも　本当ですか
Those are rumors, purely rumors.
あくまで噂だぜ　噂
However, one thing is certain: such rumors
have been whispered about her for a full 50 years.
ただ　一つ確かな事は
そういった噂は50年も前から囁かれているんだ
"50 years"?!
50年
So that means...
ってことは
50 years ago she was already a White Whistle?!
50も前から　白笛だったってこと
She truly is the Unmovable Sovereign.
What an amazing person.
まさに「不動卿」だな　すごい人だよ
However...
ただなぁ
Hey, Habo, just what Relic is it
that Ozen's armed with?
なあ　ハボさん
オーゼンの武装ってどんな遺物
I can't tell you that.
それは言えんわ
Don't give me that face.
そんな顔するなよ
White Whistles are the trump cards
of this here city of the pit.
白笛は　穴の街の切り札だ
Until their whistles return home,
that information won't be made public.
笛が帰らない限り　公にはされないんだぜ
Dang.
Ozen...
オーゼン
I don't think there's any way
she'd tell them about the Vessel...
まさか「籠」の事は言わないと思うが
but I'm still nervous.
不安だ
Perhaps I should've gone with them
despite their objections after all.
やはり　無理にでもついて行くべきだったか
I'm counting on you, Reg.
頼んだぞレグ
If it comes down to it,
you're the only one who can protect her.
もしもの時　守ってやれるのはお前だけだ
What's this cube here?
なんだ　この四角いのは
This pattern is incredibly complex...
すごく複雑な模様　二級以上の遺物
Seems to be at least a grade-2 Relic.
But, in the guide to recorded Relics...
けど　遺物録にこんなのは
Right, it's not listed.
そう　載ってないよ
It's something that Lyza personally bought
before it could be auctioned off.
競売にかけられる前に　ライザが買い取ったものさ
I'm the one who carried it here, though.
ここに運んだのは私だが
もしかして　呪い除けの籠
Could this be... the Curse-Repelling Vessel?
You're half right.
半分当たり
The "Curse-Repelling Vessel."
詛い除けの籠
From the depths up toward the surface...
深層から上へ渡りができない生き物をこれに入れて引き上げると
When living creatures that couldn't make that trip
were placed inside it and carried up,
they weren't affected by the strain of ascending
and didn't die, which is why it got the name it did.
上昇負荷を受けずに死ななかったから
そう呼ばれてた
けど　実は違ったんだよ
But, that's not actually right.
In fact, whatever's placed inside
still gets affected by the Curse and dies.
実際は詛いも受けるし　死にもする
However, it starts moving around.
ただ　動き出すんだよ
It was thanks to you that I came to understand that.
それが分かったのは　君のおかげさ
Huh?
You were stillborn, you know.
君　死産だったんだよ
When Lyza delivered you, you were already dead.
ライザから取り上げた時　もう死んでたんだ
Basically, you were a real annoyance, so I shoved you
inside this thing, but you somehow started to move.
それが　邪魔臭いからこの中に突っ込んだら
なんと動き出したのさ
Yesterday, I got nostalgic, and I tried putting some
of the meat I cook dinner with in there...
昨日　懐かしくなって
試しに晩飯に使う肉を入れてみたんだけどさ
The thing got loose and ran around.
それが走り回って逃げるんだ
After a while, it stopped moving.
しばらくしたら動かなくなってさ
But actually, one half of it continued to move, you see.
半身の方はまだ動いたとはねえ
Hey...
ねえ　君はいつまでもつのかな
I wonder how long you'll last...
Besides that, both you - after you started to move
back then - and the meat I put in there yesterday...
それとさ
あの時　動いた君も
昨日入れた肉も
attempted to head for the center of the Abyss
for some reason.
何故かアビスの中心に向かおうとしたんだよね
Hey, why's that?
ねぇ　なんで
You of all people might have an idea...
君なら知ってるんじゃないかな
君もあの肉と同じなんだろう
Aren't you essentially the same as that meat?
Master... stop this.
お師様　やめて
Why...?
どうして　そんなこと
The things you're saying...
It's about time you get the picture.
そろそろ分かってくれたまえ
I despise you.
私は君が嫌いなんだよ
What is it, you Aubade child?
何だね
「奈落の至宝」の少年
Your story is quite interesting...
あんたの話はとても興味深いが
これ以上リコを傷つけないでくれ
but don't hurt Riko any more than you already have.
Any way you look at it, you're really immature, Ozen!
いくらなんでも大人げないぞ　オーゼン
I used to hear that a lot.
それ　よく言われたよ
Hey, boy, do you have a conception of God?
ねぇ君　神様って知ってる
What are you saying all of a sudden?!
急に何を言い出すんだ
The people around here, you see,
don't really believe in God.
ここの人たちはねぇ　あまり神樣を信じないのさ
Instead, do you know what it is they believe in?
代わりに何を信じてるのか　分かる
The answer is this place - the Abyss itself.
それはここ　このアビスそのものさ
Precisely because the bottom of the netherworld
is unknown, and because it is feared,
奈落の底は未知だからこそ　畏怖れられるからこそ
it has the power to become their God.
神たりえるんだ
If it was easy to head down and return back home,
簡単に言って帰って来れたら
the value of Relics and faith in the Abyss
would quite possibly be shaken to the core.
遺物の価値も　アビスの信仰も
足下から揺らぎかねないのさ
The reason Aubades aren't listed in the guide...
「奈落の至宝」が目録に載っていないのはね
isn't because they haven't been discovered.
見つかっていないからじゃない
It's because they simply must not exist, you see.
存在しちゃいけないからさ
What's with this strength of hers?
なんだ　あの怪力は
My arm was creaking!
腕が　軋んだ
Hey, did I hear that you lost your memory?
君　記憶をなくしてるんだってね
Well, I'm truly glad.
いやぁ　本当によかった
I need to dispose of you
before you remember anything.
思い出す前に　処分しておかないとな
I-I'll go check on the telescope...
ぽ　僕　望遠鏡確認してきます
マルルク
Marulk!
Stay right there.
動くな
Y-you can't be serious!
じょ　冗談じゃない
As if I'd let things end in a place like this!
こんなところで終わってたまるか
力尽くでも行かせてもらうぞ
I'll make you let us go
even if I have to use brute force!
行かせてあげるよ
I'll let you go...
After you've ceased moving, that is!
動かなくなった後でね
全て止められない
This isn't stopping her at all!
何なんだ　あいつは
What the heck is she?!
This doesn't break or get any thinner.
千切りもせず　細かくもならない
I wonder if a bunch of strands
are all packed into the same area...
同じ領域に何重にも束ねてあるのかな
Well, whatever.
まあいいや　返すよ
Have it back.
Oh? You're lighter than I thought.
あれ　思ったより軽いな
So your sturdiness is your big appeal, right?
頑丈さが売りなんだって
試してみようかな
Let's test it out.
Oops. I busted the floor.
まずった　床をやってしまった
O-o-ouch...
い　いたた
You've really... done it now...
よくも　やったなぁ
You're a lot tougher than the floor, huh?
床よりよっぽど頑丈だね
I wonder how much more you can take...
あと何回行けるかなぁ
Stop!
やめて
Reg... Reg will break!
レグが　レグが壊れちゃう
You're in the way.
邪魔だよ
Riko! Riko!
リコ　リコ
There's so much blood...
こんなに血が
Sorry, Marulk...
すまない　マルルク
This isn't an opponent I can hold back on.
躡躇できる相手じゃない
If I don't get serious, I'm done for!
本気で行かねば　やられる
What is it you're going to show me?
何を見せてくれるんだね
If I just let it rip like last time,
the whole Seeker Camp could burn down...
あのまま出せばシーカーキャンプごとを焼きかねない
Calm down...
落ち着け
Refine it... thinner... sharper...!
絞れ　細く　鋭く
So, I see that you breathe and blink
even though you're just a mechanical doll.
君　機械人形のくせに呼吸も瞬きもするね
That means you, too,
will be probably be hunted by beasts.
そんなんじゃ獣にも狩られるだろうに
Hey, what happens when this thing hits something?
ねえ　これ　当たったらどうなるのさ
試してみよう
Let's test it out.
Oh my, incredible, isn't it?
すごいね
It blasts straight through.
消し飛ぶんだ
I've never seen a weapon like this before.
こんな火砲　お目にかかった事がない
Irredeemable!
度し難い
You're irredeemable, Ozen!
度し難いぞ　オーゼン
な　なんだその腕は
What's with your arm...?
何か埋めてあるのか
Is something embedded inside it?
This here?
これかい
They're called Thousand-Men Wedges.
「千人楔」と言ってね
I inserted them at 120 points or so all around my body...
全身で120ヶ所入れたかな
健康の秘訣だよ
They're the secret to my vigor.
For as much as you criticize me,
you're quite superhuman yourself, Ozen!
人のことをやかく言う割に
よっぽど人間離れしているぞオーゼン
色々と気を遺うのさ　歳だからね
I fuss over lots of things.
I'm old, after all.
R-Reg!
レ　レグ
You're so noisy.
煩いなぁ
If you think he's so precious,
you should've kept him locked away.
そんなに大事ならしまっておけば良かったのに
For some reason he went limp all of a sudden,
but that's alright, isn't it?
何だか急にぐったりしちゃったけど
いいじゃないか
君も遅かれ早かれ肉に戻るんだ
Sooner or later, you'll revert back
to being a piece of meat, anyway.
わ　私
I... didn't descend into the Abyss
because I hope to live a long life.
長生きしたくてアビスに潜ったんじゃない
Even just a little longer is okay!
あとちょっとでもいい
But, together with Reg...
でもレグと　レグと一緒じゃなきゃ嫌だ
If it's not with Reg... I can't bear it!
お願いレグ　負けないで
Please, Reg! Don't lose to her!
Riko...
リコ
That won't do.
ダメだね
Both of you are unfit for it.
君らは不適格だ
ほら　ちゃんと嵌ったろ
Look, it fit right in there.
He woke up!
起きた
He's awake.
起きたの
R-Riko...
リ　リコ
Reg! Reg!
レグ　レグ
Sorry, Reg!
ごめんねレグ
Y-you moved!
うご　動いたぁ
ごめ　いなくなっちゃヤだぁ
Don't leave me like that!
Did I just collapse and leave Riko all alone here...?!
リコを残したまま　倒れていたのか
Reg!
レグ　リコを
Riko is...!
Riko is in your hands now!
リコを頼んだぞ
Damn it...
くそ
Ah, that one's crying too now!
こっちも泣いちゃったよ
Ozen has made yet another one cry.
オーゼンさん　また泣かしたのぉ
Poor things...
かわいそうに
Wh-who the heck...
あ　あんたたちは 何　何なんだ
a-are you guys?!
You mean us?
俺たちかい
We're Subterranean Bandits, Ozen's cave raider squad.
「地臥せり」　オーゼンさんの探窟隊さ
They're a bunch of good-for-nothings
with nowhere to call home on the surface.
地上に帰る場所のない　ろくでなし共だよ
They were told to stay out of it,
but Marulk called them here, you see.
引っ込んでるよう言ったんだけど
マルルクに呼ばれちまったのさ
U-um...
あ　あの　僕
I...
Along with a brat who can't do anything
but cry and make a fuss,
泣いて騒ぐしかできなかった小娘に
we've got a mechanical doll who fires his weapon
without even thinking and then faints...
撃って昏倒したことがある火砲を考えなしに放つ機械人形
While those two didn't even
make a single correct decision,
彼らが何一つ正しく判断できない中で
you acted in the most appropriate manner
to save your friends.
友人を助ける為　最良の行動をしたね
さすが私の弟子だ
That's my apprentice for you.
As punishment for disobeying my orders,
I'll string you up naked later, though.
命令に背いた罰として　後で裸吊りだよ
Ozen told us to stay hidden
while the two kiddies are here.
坊主たちがいる間は隠れてろって　オーゼンさんに言われてたがよ
But the ground shook countless times.
何度も地響きはするし
And this kid also started sobbing
and came rushing over to us.
この子も　べそべそになって飛んでくるしの
I-is that right...?
そ　そうだったのか
マルルク　すまなかった
Marulk... I'm sorry.
I know you said you wanted to test Lyza's child,
but you really overdid it.
ライザさんの子を試すって言ってもよ
やりすぎだよな
Wh-what do you mean by that?!
ど　どういうことだ
Just what it sounds like.
そのまんまの意味さ
Are you saying that was all... j-just some act?!
今までのあれが　え　演技だとでも
I'm being serious.
本気さ　本気でやらなきゃ伝わらないだろ
If I don't go all out, I won't get the point across, will I?
I hate deceiving children, you know.
私は子供騙しが嫌いなんだ
Th-then...
じゃ　じゃあ
that part about disposing of the Aubade was...?
「奈落の至宝」は処分するとかは
I never had any intention of doing that, of course.
もちろんそんな気はなかったさぁ
It's just that you're too sturdy.
ただ君が頑丈過ぎてさ　いくら叩いても潰れないから
No matter how many times I hit you,
you weren't breaking, so I got more and more into it.
だんだん興奮してきちゃってねぇ
The primeval creatures that inhabit the deeper parts
of the Abyss are far more cunning and tough than I am.
アビスの深部に住む原生生物は
私より遥かに狡猾で強かだ
You won't be able to protect that girl.
君のその娘は守れないよ
Marulk, please tend to the boy.
マルルク　少年を介抱してやりたまえ
If he's able to fill his belly with human food,
then human medicine should probably work, too.
ヒトの食物で腹が膨れるならヒトの効も聞くだろう
効かなきゃ多めに食わせときな
If it doesn't work, just feed him a lot.
O-okay!
は　はい
Today's lesson is over.
今日のレッスンは終わりだよ
私は片付けがあるからね
I have some tidying up to do, you see.
ほら　せっかく集まったんだ 手伝っていきな
Hey, you're already here now,
so come on and lend me a hand.
Alrighty.
へーい
If you continue pushing on at your current skill level,
you'll just end up as poor meals or little seedbeds.
今の君らがこの先へ言ってもせいぜいなれるのは食いでの悪い餌か
小さめの苗床
あとは地面や壁の染みぐらいさ
Other than that, you'll just be
a stain on the ground or some wall.
もっとも　私が叩き直す途中でそうならないとも限らないが
That said, there's no guarantee you won't end up
like that as I'm trying to beat you into shape...
Oh, that's right. There is one thing
I was deceiving you about.
ああ　そうだ
一つだけ騙していたことがあった
That grave I spoke of...
例の墓だけどね
No one was buried there.
誰も埋まっていなかったよ
本当さ
It's true.
Did you really think I wouldn't dig it up
and see for myself?
暴いて確かめない訳ないだろ
Lyza is waiting for you.
ライザは待ってくれているさ
You at least need to give it a shot.
せいぜいやってみることだね
Riko?
リコ
Ozen... Ozen!
オーゼン
Ozen.
What's up with your hair?
その髪は　一体どうなっているんだ
Oh, you again...
また君かね
二度とも蹴られたのに懲りないね
I've already kicked you twice
but you still haven't learned your lesson.
What an unusual one you are...
珍しいのがいたもんだ
So, what's up with it, anyway?
なあ　どうなってるんだ
It's to cover up my scars, you see.
こいつはね
傷を取り繕っているのさ
As your mind comes under attack
in the depths of the Abyss,
アビスの深層で心をやられるとね
gradually the effects show up physically, too.
徐々に身体にも出ちまうんだ
They don't manifest immediately
like the sixth layer's Curse does,
六層の「詛い」ほどすぐには現れないけどね
but if you tread the boundaries of sanity
as well as life and death each time you descend,
潜る度に死線や正気の境をふらつけば
the skin on your head is bound to get all twisted.
頭の皮だって捻くれてくるもんさ
I'm just good at arranging my hair
to fool everyone, you see.
こいつは上手く整えて　誤魔化してあるだけだよ
かっこいいな
How cool!
If you don't watch what you say, I'll kick you again.
あまり適当なこと言うと　また蹴るよ
いいや　かっこいい
No, really. That's cool!
Those scars are proof of your fortitude
in continuing to challenge the netherworld,
その傷は　心圻れようと奈落に挑み続けた
even as it tried to break your mind.
不屈な証だ
Ozen the Immovable. A genuine White Whistle.
動かざるオーゼン　本物の白笛だ
Hey, will you be my mentor?
なあ　あんた　私の師匠にならないか
Ozen. Look, Ozen.
オーゼン　見ろオーゼン
I'm already a Black Whistle.
ついに黒笛だ　もうじきあんたに追いつくぞ
Before long, I'll catch up with you!
You've got some nerve to say that
considering you cried when I hit you last night.
昨晩私に叩かれて泣いてたくせに　よく言うよ
まあいいさ　ならば早速行こうかね
Very well, then. If that's the case,
let's just hurry up and go.
Starting tomorrow, the strain of the fourth layer
will make you shed tears of blood.
明日からは　四層の負荷で
流すのは血涙さ
Now that's something to look forward to.
楽しみだね
I wouldn't have it any other way!
望むところだ
Ozen, your personality is irredeemable,
but you're still the best mentor ever!
オーゼン　あんた性格は度し難いが
最高の師匠だよ
How are you feeling?
具合はどうだい
I'm alright now.
もう大丈夫だ
The next large group of cave raiders
arrives in three weeks.
次の大規模探窟隊が来るまでの三週間
I'll only be able to try beating you into shape until then,
whether or not it proves successful.
ものになろうがならなかろうが
君らを叩き直すのはそこまでだ
Where are we headed?
どこに向かっているんだ
Somewhere even further than the Seeker Camp.
シーカーキャンプのさらに奥さ
It's the outer edge of the Abyss, so to speak.
言ってみりゃ　アビスの端だね
Out there, there's no worry of running into other
cave raiders or having anyone come to your rescue.
そこなら他の探窟隊どもに見つかる心配も
助けがくる心配もない
訓練にはもってこいなのさ
It's ideal for training, you see.
Training...
訓練
最初の課題は　「生存訓練」だ
Your first assignment is what I call "survival training."
Most of the creatures are quite docile here,
ここは　力場の光も届かないせいか　生物も大人しい奴が殆どさ
perhaps because the force field's light
doesn't make it here.
Even so, the creatures here can see in the dark,
so keep your guard up.
それでも夜目の効く奴ばかりだから
油断しないことだね
Spend ten days here with the equipment you've got.
Show me you're able to survive.
その装備で十日間　生き延びてみせな
あの「はしらの木」から向こうへは行かないように
Be sure not to go beyond that Pillar Tree.
I'll consider that as trying to escape.
逃げたとみなすからね
それじゃ　私は帰るよ
Well then, I'm heading back now.
Huh?!
Do your best to protect this girl
so that she doesn't return to being a corpse.
この子を死体に戻さないよう　せいぜい守ってやるんだね
In addition, you can't use that thing for these ten days.
それと
そいつを1０日間　使うのはなしだ
My Incinerator?
火葬砲を
Go ahead and use it if you want to get Riko killed.
リコを死なせたいなら　使ってもいいよ
What do you mean?
どういうこと
Once you fire it, no matter how you push yourself,
you always faint after around ten minutes.
撃ったが最後
君はどんなに気張っても10分程度で昏倒
Then it's a full two hours until you wake up.
目覚めるまで　たっぷり二時間かかる
During that time, even if I punched you,
slapped you against the floor,
その間は私が殴ろうが　床に叩きつけようが水に沈めようが
or dunked you in water, you still didn't get up.
起き上がりやしなかった
Just try leaving a helpless child on her own
in the second layer for two hours.
深層で二時間無力な子供を放置して見なよ
I wonder just how she'll be torn to shreds and eaten...
どんな風に食い散らかされるかねえ
Still, when you really do have to use it,
ま　それでおまえやらなきゃいけない時は
go all out to make sure whatever it is
doesn't come after you again in the future.
後腐れが残らないように徹底てきになるんだね
No matter your opponent or whatever lies in the vicinity,
相手が誰であろうと周りに何があろうと
when the time comes, don't hesitate or show any mercy.
その時が来たら躡躇も容赦も無しだ
Otherwise, your adventure will be over
in the blink of an eye.
さもなきゃ　君らの冒険が終わるのなんて　あっという間さ
The glittering waves that float in the sky
空に浮かんでる光る波を束ねて虹の橋をかけよう
Let's bundle them and build a rainbow bridge
危うい足場 滑るスロープ
A dangerous foothold, a slope we slide on
A signpost of the past and future
過去と未来の道標
君の左手 僕の右手を
Your left hand, with my right hand
Join it, connect us, and let's begin
繫いで繫げてはじめよう
いつも そばに いるよ
I am always beside you
過去も 今も 未来も
In the past, the present, and also the future
So let's walk along without hesitating
だから迷わずに歩いていこう
色とりどりの夢 重ねて
Pile up multicolored dreams
明日はどこに向かう
Where will we head toward tomorrow?
君と一緒にいれたら 世界は輝きだすよ
If I can be together with you, the world will begin to shine
最果ての地に咲く花を探そう
Let's search for flowers that bloom at the ends of the earth
Next Episode
Survival Training